Where your nightmares end...
Eraserhead is a horror, drama film directed by David Lynch.
First-time father Henry Spencer tries to survive his industrial environment, his angry
girlfriend, and the unbearable screams of his newly born mutant child.
Henry Spencer, played by Jack Nance.
Mary X, played by Charlotte Stewart.
Mr. X, played by Allen Joseph.
Mrs. X, played by Jeanne Bates.
Beautiful Girl Across the Hall, played by Judith Roberts.
Lady in the Radiator, played by Laurel Near.
Eraserhead is a 1977 American body horror film written, directed, produced, and
edited by David Lynch in his feature-length directorial debut.
Lynch also created its score and sound design, which
included pieces by a variety of other musicians.
Shot in black and white and surrealist style, the independent film was
Lynch's first feature-length effort following several short films.
Starring Jack Nance, Charlotte Stewart, Jeanne Bates, Judith Anna Roberts, Laurel Near, and Jack Fisk, it tells the story
of a man (Nance) who is left to care for his grossly deformed child in a desolate industrial landscape.
Eraserhead was produced with the assistance of the American Film
Institute (AFI) during Lynch's time studying there.
It nonetheless spent several years in principal photography because of funding difficulties; donations from Fisk and
his wife Sissy Spacek as well as Nance's wife and crew member Catherine Coulson kept production afloat.
It was shot on several locations owned by the AFI in California, including
Greystone Mansion, and a set of disused stables in which Lynch lived.
Lynch and sound designer Alan Splet spent a year working on the
film's audio after their studio was soundproofed.
The soundtrack features organ music by Fats Waller and includes the song "In Heaven",
written and performed for the film by Peter Ivers, with lyrics by Lynch.
Initially opening to small audiences and little interest, Eraserhead
gained popularity over several long runs as a midnight movie.
Since its release, it has received widespread acclaim from
critics and has been considered a cult film.
Its surrealist imagery and sexual undercurrents have been seen as key thematic
elements, and its intricate sound design as its technical highlight.
In 2004, the film was selected by the Library of Congress for preservation in the United States
National Film Registry as being "culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant".
The film explores themes of baby, nightmare,
mutant, claustrophobia, parents-in-law.
The tone is dark and emotional and mind_bending.